<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[The primer in English.]</title>
            <title>Book of hours. English</title>
            <author>Church of England.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1545</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 7 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A05824</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 16033.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S107937</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99843629</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99843629</idno>
            <idno type="VID">8374</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A05824)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 8374)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 112:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>[The primer in English.]</title>
                  <title>Book of hours. English</title>
                  <author>Church of England.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8] leaves   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Rychard Grafyton dwellynge within the circuite of the late Grayfryers, prynter to the Prynces grace,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Imprynted in London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1545?]]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Title from STC.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon; STC suggests publication date as 1544-1545.</note>
                  <note>Based on STC 16015, a composite version--STC.</note>
                  <note>Formerly STC 16031.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 16031 on UMI microfilm.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; a fragment; 8 leaves from quires t-u only.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Primers (Prayer-books) --  Church of England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Books of hours --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:8374:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8374:1"/>
            <head>The Dirige.</head>
            <p>BLeſſed is he that con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſidereth the pore, the Lorde ſhall delyuer hym in the tyme of trouble.</p>
            <p>Thou ſhalt preſerue hym and kepe him aliue, he ſhal make him to proſper vpon erth, &amp; ſhal not deliuer him to the wyl of his enemyes.</p>
            <p>The Lord ſhal refeeſh him when he lyeth ſycke vpon his bedde, yea, thou makeſt his bed in all his ſickenes.</p>
            <p>I ſayed Lorde be merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full vnto my ſoule, for I haue ſynned agaynſt the.</p>
            <p>Myne enemies ſpeake euil
<pb facs="tcp:8374:2"/>vpon me: whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhal he die, &amp; when ſhal his name periſh.</p>
            <p>Thoughe he came into ſe, yet mened he falſhed in his hert <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>apyng myſchife vp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>p<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> hym ſelfe.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>l thei that hate me, ru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne in together agaynſte me, &amp; ymagined euil agaynſt me.</p>
            <p>Thei haue geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a wycked ſentence vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ly<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eth, he ſhal riſe vp nomore.</p>
            <p>Yea, ene<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> myne owne famy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lier frendes who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I truſted which did eat my b<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d hath lift vp his hele againſt me.</p>
            <p>But be thou merciful vnto
<pb facs="tcp:8374:2"/>me (O Lord) raiſe thou me vp, and I ſhal reward the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            <p>By this I knowe thou fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uoreſt me, that mine enemy ſhal not triumph ouer me.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hou haſt holden me, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of myne innocencie, and ſet me before thy face for euer.</p>
            <p>O bleſſed be the Lord God of Iſrael from henſeforth &amp; euermore, ſo be it, ſo be it <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Heale my ſoule Lord, for I haue ſynned a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gaynſt the.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:8374:3"/>
               <head>Quemadmodum deſi.</head>
               <p>Lyke as the hart deſy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>reth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> waterbrokes, ſo longeth my ſoule after the o God.</p>
               <p>My ſoule is thruſtye for God, euen for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> liuing fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tayn, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhal I come and behold the face of God.</p>
               <p>My teares are my meate day and nyght whyle it is daily ſaied vnto me, where is no we thy God.</p>
               <p>Now when I thinke ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pon I poure out my hart <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſelfe, for <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap>ld<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8374:3"/>immortalitee.</p>
               <p>But when this corrupti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble ſhal put on incorrupcio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and this mortall ſhall put on immortalitee, then ſhal that worde bee fulfylled whiche is wrytten. Deathe is ſwalowed vp in victory</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Anſwere</label> We ſhall all be brought before the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſeate of Chryſt wher euery one of vs ſhall geue accomptes for him felf vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to God.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Verſicle.</label> And he ſhal rewarde euery man ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordynge to his dedes.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 chunk">
                        <desc>…</desc>
                     </gap>ion.</label> Where euery
<pb facs="tcp:8374:4"/>man ſhall geue accompte.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </head>
               <p>I Wolde not brethren that ye ſhulde be igno<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>raunt concernynge theim that are fallen a ſleye, that ye ſorowe not as other do whiche haue no hope, for yf we beleue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Ieſus dyed and roſe againe. Euen ſo they alſo whiche ſlepe by Ieſus ſhal God brynge w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> him, for this we ſaye vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you in the worde of th<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8374:4"/>Lorde, that we which lyue and are remayninge in the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>minge of the Lorde, ſhal not come yer they whiche ſlepe, for the Lorde ſhall come downe from heauen with a ſhoute and voice of the Archaungell and with the trompe of GOD, and the deade in Chryſt <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hall ariſe fyrſte, then ſhall we whiche lyue and remayne, be caught vp with theim alſo in the <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap>es to mete the Lorde in the a<gap reason="illegible" extent="2+ letters">
                     <desc>••…</desc>
                  </gap>e, and ſo ſhal we euer be with the <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>orde. Wherfore co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forte
<pb facs="tcp:8374:5"/>your ſelues one another with theſe wordes.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</label> Nowe is Chriſt riſen from the dead and is become the fyrſt fru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that ſlepe, for by one man co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth deathe, &amp; by one man the reſurreci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the dead, for as they all die in Ada<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſo ſhall they al be made a lyue in Chriſt but euery one in his order</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Verſicle.</label> The firſte is Chriſt, then they that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longe vnto Chriſt when he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Repetition.</label> Eue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry one in his order.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8374:5"/>
                  <label>
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </label> Nowe Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s, we moſt hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bly beſeche &amp; thou which art come to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deme wretches fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſynne &amp; thraldome, wilt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> caſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> haſt ſo dere<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly redemed.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </label> O Lorde deliuer me fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting death at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dredfull day whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; earth ſhal be altered, whiles y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſhalte come to iudge the worlde.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>The a<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 chunk">
                        <desc>…</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </label> My bruſed.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</head>
               <p>Miſerere mei deꝰ.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>
                     <abbr>Anth</abbr>
                  </label>. My bruſed bones Lorde
<pb facs="tcp:8374:6"/>ſhalbe refreſhed. Heare my prayer.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </head>
               <head>Te decet hymnus.</head>
               <p>THou (O God) arte prayſed in Sio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; to the is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vowe perfourmed Thou heareſt the prayer, therfore commeth al fleſhe vnto the.</p>
               <p>Our miſdedes preuayle a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gainſt vs, oh be thou mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful vnto our ſinnes.</p>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>leſſed is the man who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> choſeſt &amp; receiueſt vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>, that he maye dwell in thy court: he ſhalbe ſatiſfied w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the<gap reason="missing" extent="1+ pages">
                     <desc>〈1… pages missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8374:6"/>his webbe.</p>
               <p>While I was yet takinge my reſt he hewed me of, &amp; made an ende of me in one daye.</p>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> thought, I wolde haue lyued vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> morowe, but he bruſed my bones lyke a Lyon, and made an ende of me in one day.</p>
               <p>Then chattered I lyke a ſwalowe, and like a crane and mourned as <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> doue.</p>
               <p>I lift vp mine e<gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hight O Lord (ſ<gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> I) vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olence is done vn<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o me, be thou ſu<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tie for me.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8374:7"/>
What ſhal I ſpeke or ſay that he may do this that I may lyue out all my yeres, yea, in the bitternes of my lyfe.</p>
               <p>Verely (Lorde) men muſt liue in bitternes, and al my lyfe muſt I paſſe ouer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, for thou rayſeſt, me and wakeneſt me, but I wil be well content with this byt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ternes.</p>
               <p>Neuertheleſſe my conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſacion hath ſo pleaſed the that y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> wouldeſt not make an ende of my life, ſo that thou haſt caſt my ſinnes be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>hinde
<pb facs="tcp:8374:7"/>thy backe.</p>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or hell prayſeth not the death doth not magnifie y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hey that go downe into the graue prayſe not thy truth, but the lyuinge:yea, the lyuing acknowledge y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> lyke as I dooe this day, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> father telleth his chyldren of thy faythfulnes.</p>
               <p>Deliuer vs (O Lord) and we wyl ſing prayſes in thi houſe all the daies of oure life.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</label> Fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gates of hell, Lorde deliuer them.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</label> Let euery ſpirits geue prayſe vnto the Lord</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8374:8"/>
                  <label>Ps</label>
Laudate <abbr>dnm</abbr> de celis.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Ver.</label> Fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the gates of hel.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Anſwer.</label> Lord deliuer their ſoules.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>An<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 chunk">
                        <desc>…</desc>
                     </gap>.</label> I am the reſurreccion &amp; life, he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leueth in me, yea although he were deade, yet ſhall he liue, and whoſoeuer liueth and beleueth in me, ſhall not ſe euerlaſtynge death.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Pſalme <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </label> Benedictus <abbr>dns</abbr>.</p>
               <p>Lorde haue mercy on vs.</p>
               <p>Chriſt haue mercy on vs.</p>
               <p>L<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>de haue mercy on vs.</p>
               <p>Our father. And leade vs not. But deliuer vs.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ The <gap reason="illegible" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> Pſalme</head>
               <p>Exaltabo <gap reason="missing" extent="1+ pages">
                     <desc>〈1… pages missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:8374:8"/>
               <p>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mynge of thy ſonne our Lorde Chryſt, we with all other faythful people may be graciouſly brought vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ioyes euerlaſtinge, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che ſhalt come to iudge both the quicke and deade. By Chriſt our Lorde. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <pb facs="tcp:8374:9"/>
            <p>¶ Imprynted in London by Ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charde <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> dwel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lynge within the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuite of the late <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> prynter to the <unclear>Prynces</unclear> grace<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <p>(<g ref="char:cross">✚</g>)</p>
         </div>
         <div xml:lang="lat" type="license">
            <p>Cum priuilegio ad imprimendu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſolum</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:8374:9"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
